A Guide to the Poe Foundation Business records, 1913-2008
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Poe Foundation Business records, 1913-2008
The Library of Virginia
43972
15.1 cu. ft. (45 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Poe Museum, Richmond, Virginia September 2008.
Biographical Information
The Old Stone House, or the Edgar Allan Poe Museum, opened in April 1922 in Richmond, Virginia. The Poe Museum contains the world's largest collection of Edgar Allan Poe's manuscripts, letters, first editions, memorabilia, and personal belongings. The first officers were J. H. Whitty, President, and W.G. Stanard and Douglas Freeman, Vice Presidents. In 2009 the museum will celebrate the 200th anniversary of the birth of Edgar Allen Poe.
Scope and Content
Business records, 1913-2008, of the Edgar Allan Poe Museum of Richmond, Virginia. Includes admission ledgers, annual reports and minutes, book shop accounts, card catalogs, correspondence, daily journals, finances, guest registers, newsletters, photographs, programs, and receipts.
Of note are the numerous letters from Poe scholars, board members, donors, and various dignitaries, including presidents and senators. Beginning in 1921 the museum embarked on an initiative to collect Poe memorabilia and personal effects, and letters tracing these efforts are included. The correspondence also includes numerous requests for information on Poe and purchases from the book shop, as well as copies of poetry and stories submitted by Poe scholars. Also included are letters appointing board members and announcing board meetings, and membership dues. Included is an interesting collection of letters from Olaf Bjorkman regarding a sculpture of Poe and the Raven. Other correspondents include: William Sumner Appleton, Senator Harry F. Byrd, James Branch Cabell, Douglas S. Freeman, Honorable Vaughan Gary, President Warren G. Harding, John Calvin Metcalf, Bentley Munford, George Foster Peabody, Senator A. Willis Robertson, Chief Justice William H. Taft, Morton G. Thalhimer, Mary Traylor (secretary), and Governor William M. Tuck.
The annual reports, 1922-1974, include financial statements, minutes, tour notes, meeting announcements, and reports to the president and board members. Included are copies of the newsletters, Evermore and The Poe Messenger. The financial organization of the museum can be traced through the account cash ledgers, annual reports, book shop accounts, daily journals, and receipts. Also of note are the guest registers, 1921-2006, which record visitors to the Poe Museum, including celebrities such as Gertrude Stein, and track the attendance and popularity of the museum. The collection also includes card catalogs containing information on donations, lists of books, pamphlets, and articles located at the Poe museum, and miscellaneous card catalogs.
Arrangement
This collection is alphabetically by folder title, with the card catalogs arranged at the end.
Contents List
- Accession register, 1976-1997. (Box 1)
  (see also the accession file card catalogs)
- Accession register, 1998-2006. (Box 1)
- Account and membership ledger, 1923. (Box 1)
- Admissions cash ledger, 1975 November-1980 January. (Box 1)
- Admissions cash ledger, 1980 January-1982 January. (Box 1)
- Admissions cash ledger, 1982 January-1983 October. (Box 1)
- Admissions cash ledger, 1985 May-1987 January. (Box 1)
- Admissions cash ledger, 1987 January-1988 August. (Box 1)
- Admissions cash ledger, 1990 April-1991 November. (Box 1)
- Admissions cash ledger, 1991 November-1993 June. (Box 1)
- Admissions cash ledger, 1993 June-1994 May. (Box 1)
- Advertisements, Events, 1977. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Annual reports and minutes, 1922-1925. (Box 2, Folder 1a)
- Annual reports and minutes, 1926-1927. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Annual reports and minutes, 1930-1939. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Annual reports and minutes, 1940-1949. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Annual reports and minutes, 1950-1959. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Annual reports and minutes, 1960-1974. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Appraisal, nd. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Articles of incorporation, 1922-1982. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Board members, 1954-1978. (Box 2, Folder 8a)
- Book shop account journal, 1923 October-1929 December. (Box 2a)
- Book shop account journal, 1962 November-1964 June. (Box 2a)
- Book shop account journal, 1972 August-1974 March. (Box 2a)
- Clippings, 1945-2005. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1913-1918. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1920. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1921. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1922 January-June. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1922 July-December. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1922-1931. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Olaf Bjorkman
- Correspondence, 1923 January-June. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1923 July-December. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1924 January-June. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1924 July-December. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1925 January-June. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1925 July-December. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1926 January-June. (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1926 July-September. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1926 October-December. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1927 January-June. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1927 July-December. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1928 January-June. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1928 July-December. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1929 January-June. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1929 July-December. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, Davenport Insurance Co., 1921-1925. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, Davenport Insurance Co., 1926-1934. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1930 January-June. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1930 July-December. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1931. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1932. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1933. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1934. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1935. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1936. (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1937. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1938. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1939. (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1940. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1941. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1942. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1943. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1944. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1945. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1949. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1958-1959. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1960-1964. (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1965-1969. (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1970-1979. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1980-1986. (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1987. (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1988-1989. (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1990-1997. (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 2000-2006. (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, nd. (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Daily journal/diary, 1962. (Box 8)
- Daily journal/diary, 1962. (Box 8)
- Daily journal/diary, 1963. (Box 8)
- Daily journal/diary, 1962 October-1963 September. (Box 8a, Folder 1)
- Daily journal/diary, 1963 October-1964 September. (Box 8a, Folder 2)
- Daily journal/diary, 1964 October-1965 December. (Box 8a, Folder 3)
- Daily journal/diary, 1976-1977. (Box 8)
- Daily journal/diary, 1978. (Box 8)
- Daily journal/diary, 1987. (Box 8)
- Donations, 1989-2006. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Exhibit loans, 1993. (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Finances, 1925-1933. (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Financial report, 1932. (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Financial report, 1955-1960. (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Financial report, 1975. (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Financial report, 1990-2008. (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Genealogy, Poe family. (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Histories/biographies of Poe. (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Histories/biographies of Poe, Museum package. (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Guest register, 1921 October-1926 April. (Box 9)
- Guest register, 1926 April-1929 April. (Box 10)
- Guest register, 1929 April-1932 March. (Box 11)
- Guest register, 1932 March-1936 July. (Box 12)
- Guest register, 1936 September-1939 October. (Box 13)
- Guest register, 1939 October-1943 September. (Box 14)
- Guest register, 1944 May-1947 August. (Box 15)
- Guest register, 1947 August-1951 November. (Box 16)
- Guest register, 1954 May-1955 August. (Box 17)
- Guest register, 1955 August-1956 May. (Box 17)
- Guest register, 1956 May-1957 August. (Box 17)
- Guest register, 1957 August-1959 May. (Box 17)
- Guest register, 1959 May-1960 October. (Box 17)
- Guest register, 1960 October-1962 April. (Box 18)
- Guest register, 1962 May-1963 April. (Box 18)
- Guest register, 1963 April-1964 March. (Box 18)
- Guest register, 1964 March-October. (Box 18)
- Guest register, 1964 October-1965 August. (Box 19)
- Guest register, 1965 August-1966 June. (Box 19)
- Guest register, 1966 June-December. (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Guest register, 1966 December-1967 December. (Box 20, Folder 2)
- Guest register, 1967 December-1968 December. (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Guest register, 1968 December-1969 December. (Box 20, Folder 4)
- Guest register, 1969 December-1970 December. (Box 20, Folder 5)
- Guest register, 1970 December-1971 December. (Box 20, Folder 6)
- Guest register, 1971 December-1972 December. (Box 21, Folder 1)
- Guest register, 1972 December-1973 December. (Box 21, Folder 2)
- Guest register, 1973 December-1974 December. (Box 21, Folder 3)
- Guest register, 1975 January-June. (Box 21, Folder 4)
- Guest register, 1975 July-December. (Box 21, Folder 5)
- Guest register, 1976 January-December. (Box 22, Folder 1)
- Guest register, 1977 January-December. (Box 22, Folder 2)
- Guest register, 1978 January-December. (Box 22, Folder 3)
- Guest register, 1979 January-December. (Box 22, Folder 4)
- Guest register, 1980 January-December. (Box 23, Folder 1)
- Guest register, 1981 January-December. (Box 23, Folder 2)
- Guest register, 1982 January-December. (Box 23, Folder 3)
- Guest register, 1983 January-December. (Box 23, Folder 4)
- Guest register, 1984 January-December. (Box 23, Folder 5)
- Guest register, 1985 January-December. (Box 24, Folder 1)
- Guest register, 1986 January-December. (Box 24, Folder 2)
- Guest register, 1987 January-December. (Box 24, Folder 3)
- Guest register, 1988 January-December. (Box 24, Folder 4)
- Guest register, 1989 January-December. (Box 24, Folder 5)
- Guest register, 1990 January-December. (Box 25, Folder 1)
- Guest register, 1991 January-December. (Box 25, Folder 2)
- Guest register, 1992 January-December. (Box 25, Folder 3)
- Guest register, 1993 August-1994 March. (Box 25, Folder 4)
- Guest register, 1994 March-1995 January. (Box 25, Folder 5)
- Guest register, 1995 January-October. (Box 26, Folder 1)
- Guest register, 1995 October-1996 March. (Box 26, Folder 2)
- Guest register, 1996 March-October. (Box 26, Folder 3)
- Guest register, 1996 October-1997 June. (Box 26, Folder 4)
- Guest register, 1999 March-October. (Box 26, Folder 5)
- Guest register, 2000 March-2001 January. (Box 26, Folder 6)
- Guest register, 2001 January-2004 January. (Box 26, Folder 7)
- Guest register, 2004 January-2006 April. (Box 26, Folder 8)
- Long range interpretive plan, 2003. (Box 27, Folder 1)
- Mail account ledger, 1975-1977. (Box 27, Folder 2)
- Manuals/museum guides, 1969-1978. (Box 27, Folder 3)
- Membership, 1926-c. 1950. (Box 27, Folder 4)
- Memorial contributions ledger, 1976-1980. (Box 27, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous. (Box 27, Folder 6)
- Newsletters, Evermore, 1998-2006. (Box 27, Folder 7)
- Newsletters, The Edgar Allan Poe Museum, 1985. (Box 27, Folder 8)
- Newsletters, The Poe Messenger, 1969-1973. (Box 27, Folder 9)
- Newsletters, The Poe Messenger, 1974-1975. (Box 27, Folder 10)
- Newsletters, The Poe Messenger, 1977-1978. (Box 27, Folder 11)
- Newsletters, The Poe Messenger, 1988. (Box 27, Folder 12)
- Newsletters, The Poe Messenger, 1992. (Box 27, Folder 13)
- Newsletters, The Poe Messenger, Notes, etc., 1973-1978. (Box 28, Folder 1)
- Newsletters, Miscellaneous, 1983. (Box 28, Folder 2)
- Pamphlets, The Edgar Allan Poe Museum, c. 1970-1990. (Box 28, Folder 3)
- Pamphlets, Richmond Walking Tour, ca. 1970. (Box 28, Folder 4)
- Pamphlets, Miscellaneous, ca. 1940-1790. (Box 28, Folder 5)
- Permission forms, 1941-2005. (Box 28, Folder 6)
- Petty cash ledger, 1963-1975. (Box 28, Folder 7)
- Photographs, Labeling of James William Carlings unmarked grave, 1984. (Box 28, Folder 8)
- Photographs, Douglas Southall Freeman, ca. 1950. (Box 28, Folder 9)
- Photographs, Mrs. William Northrop home "Norcroft", ca. 1940-1950. (Box 28, Folder 10)
- Photographs, Poe Shrine/Museum building and furniture, 1978. (Box 28, Folder 11)
- Photographs, Miscellaneous, ca. 1960. (Box 28, Folder 12)
- Photographs, Transparencies, nd. (Box 28, Folder 13)
- Plat of Richmond (copy), nd. (Box 28, Folder 14)
- Policies regarding gifts, loans, and appraisals, 1979. (Box 28, Folder 15)
- Programs, "None Sings So Wildly Well", An Evocation of the World of Edgar Allan Poe, nd. (Box 28, Folder 16)
- Programs, International Edgar Allan Poe Conference, 1999. (Box 28, Folder 17)
- Programs, Miscellaneous, 1937. (Box 28, Folder 18)
- Proposal, Biggs Antique Company, 1962. (Box 28, Folder 19)
- Receipts, 1923-1971. (Box 28, Folder 20)
- Richmond Passport, 1983. (Box 28, Folder 20a)
- Short stories of J.E. Orschel, nd. (Box 28, Folder 21)
- Sketches, nd. (Box 28, Folder 22)
- State license application, 1925. (Box 28, Folder 23)
- Stationary, Poe Museum postcards, envelopes, nd. (Box 28, Folder 24)
- Stationary, The Witty Bookstore (blank). (Box 29, Folder 1-2)
- Tax returns, 1992-1993. (Box 29, Folder 3)
- Time line, 1920-1979. (Box 29, Folder 3a)
- Virginia State Travel Service, 1971. (Box 29, Folder 4)
- Workmen's compensation policy, 1974-1977. (Box 29, Folder 5)
- Exhibition labels, nd. (Box 29, Folder 6)
- Card catalogs, Accession file (numerical), 1921-1975. (Box 30-31)
- Card catalogs, Accession file (numerical), 1976-2005. (Box 32-33)
- Card catalogs, Materials housed in Poe Museum (alphabetical). (Box 34-37)
- Card catalogs, Materials housed in Poe Museum (subject). (Box 38-40)
- Card catalogs, Materials housed in The Library of Virginia (alphabetical). (Box 41-43)
- Card catalogs, Museum board members, ca. 1975-1979. (Box 44)
- Card catalogs, Magazines, pamphlets, miscellaneous (alphabetical). (Box 44)